Guide to the Nicholas Scoppetta Papers 1974-2015 MS 3017
New-York Historical Society
Nicholas Scoppetta papers
1974-2015
New-York Historical Society
Scoppetta, Nicholas, 1932-2016
MS 3017
10 Linear feet (10 record cartons and 1 oversize folder)
Personal files of New York City public official and educator Nicholas Scoppetta (1932–2016), who served as Commissioner of Investigation for the City of New York (1972–1977), Deputy Mayor for Criminal Justice (1976–1978), Professor at New York University School of Law (1978–1982), President of the Board of Trustees, Children's Aid Society (1987–1993), Commissioner of the Administration for Children's Services (1996-2001), and 31st Commissioner of the Fire Department of the City of New York (2002–2009). Includes some photographs and memorabilia.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Susan Scoppetta, widow of Nicholas Scoppetta, 2016.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers EXCEPT for Box 6, Folder 12, which is RESTRICTED until 2070 because it contains confidential material on the murder of Elisa Izquierdo.
Materials are stored offsite and advance notice is required for use. Note that some boxes are heavy.
Photocopying undertaken by staff only. Limited to twenty exposures of stable, unbound material per day. (Researchers may not accrue unused copy amounts from previous days.)
Arrangement
The collection is organized in four series with the following subdivisions:
Series I. Criminal Justice, 1974-2015 (bulk, 1978-1982)
Subseries I.A. Criminal Justice: General, 1974-2015
Subseries I.B. Criminal Justice: Teaching Material, 1978-1982
Subseries I.C. Criminal Justice: Printed Material, 1941-2000
Series II. Child Welfare, 1988-2014 (bulk, 1988-2008)
Subseries II.A. Child Welfare: General, 1988-2014
Subseries II.B. Child Welfare: Printed Material, 1982-2012
Subseries II.C. Child Welfare: Audiovisual, 1996-2002
Series III. FDNY, 2001-2015 (bulk, 2002-2009)
Subseries III.A. FDNY: General, 2001-2015
Subseries III.B. FDNY: Audiovisual, 2002-2009
Series IV. Memorabilia, 1970s-circa 2009 (bulk, 2002-2009)
Subseries IV.A. Memorabilia: Photographs and awards, 1970s-2001
Subseries IV.B. Memorabilia: Political and lapel pins, commemorative medals, etc., 1978-2009
Material is sorted chronologically throughout each series and subseries, except for those groups of folders that were originally housed in accordion files. These files (among the few that Scoppetta labeled with any consistency) come at the end of the "General" subdivisions (see the container lists for Subseries I.A, II.A, and III.A, below). Labels have been transcribed as found, with clarification added in brackets.
All audiovisual material (for which N-YHS lacks playback equipment) is housed in Boxes 9 and 10.
Scope and Contents
Nicholas Scoppetta kept these files from each of his significant career roles over the last forty-odd years of his working life: Commissioner of Investigation for the City of New York (1972–1977), Deputy Mayor for Criminal Justice (1976–1978), Professor at New York University School of Law (1978–1982), Commissioner of the Administration for Children's Services (1996-2001), and 31st Commissioner of the Fire Department of the City of New York (2002–2009). Also present is material from his long association with the Children's Aid Society, and from New Yorkers for Children, the non-profit arm of the Administration for Children's Services he founded in 1996.
Note that these appear to be Scoppetta's personal files, not his official working documents (which are likely still housed with their respective agencies), and so provide spotty coverage of his myriad duties. The researcher interested in a specific activity or event in Scoppetta's career should consult the chronological arrangement of the series described below to determine where information is likely to be found.
Much of the collection is printed matter: press releases and digests, internal memos, e-mail printouts, funeral and dedicatory programs, annual reports, conference proceedings, course readings, and so on. A number of Scoppetta's speeches and addresses, in draft and finished form—some with manuscript emendations—are scattered throughout. There is very little correspondence.
The collection includes a large amount of audiovisual material—VHS tapes, audiocassettes, CDs and DVDs—most of it on the theme of child welfare (see Subseries II.C in the container list, below).
Memorabilia in the form of photographs (of Scoppetta with significant figures like Mayor Abraham Beame and First Lady Barbara Bush), awards (including one signed by Hillary Rodham Clinton as United States Senator from New York), political pins (e.g., "NICK SCOPPETTA FOR ATTORNEY GENERAL" from his unsuccessful 1978 bid for that office), and lapel pins (many with post-9/11 sentiments) rounds out the collection (see Series IV in the container list, below).
Biographical/Historical Note
Nicholas Scoppetta was born on 6 November 1932 in Manhattan to Italian immigrants Dominick and Margaret (Rubino) Scoppetta. Dominick was a struggling vegetable merchant and dock worker. In 1937 Margaret was arrested for forging a signature on a welfare check. She pleaded guilty to a misdemeanor petty larceny charge and was sentenced to 90 days' detention. Because of this the three youngest Scoppetta sons, including Nicholas, age five, were removed from the household and placed in foster care. The boys were reunited at Woodycrest, a Bronx orphanage run by the American Female Guardian Society and Home for the Friendless. Nicholas returned to his parents at age twelve, and graduated from Seward Park High School in 1950. His later studies at City College were interrupted by the Korean War. After the Army he attended Bradley University in Peoria, Illinois, on the G.I. Bill, graduating in 1958 with a degree in civil engineering.
Back in New York Scoppetta worked by day for the Society for the Prevention of Cruelty to Children (the same agency that placed him in foster care) and attended Brooklyn Law School by night. He graduated in 1962 and was admitted to the New York State Bar that year. Shortly after, he was appointed an Assistant District Attorney in New York County by District Attorney Frank Hogan. He served in the Manhattan D.A.'s Office until 1969, when he became Assistant United States Attorney for the Southern District of New York.
In 1971 Mayor John Lindsay appointed Scoppetta Associate Counsel to the Commission to Investigate Alleged Police Corruption (a.k.a. the Knapp Commission), which issued its report in 1972. On 1 December Lindsay named Scoppetta Commissioner of Investigation for the City of New York, an appointment renewed by Lindsay's successor, Abraham Beame, in 1974.
On 1 August 1974 New York City Controller Harrison J. Goldin accused Scoppetta of "instructing" a civil servant to enter false information on the Controller's books to deceive auditors. Scoppetta was cleared of any wrongdoing by New York State Special Prosecutor Maurice H. Nadjari.
On 6 December 1976 Mayor Beame named Scoppetta to the newly created post of Deputy Mayor for Criminal Justice, a post he held concurrently as Commissioner of Investigation until 5 January 1978, when he was relieved by incoming Mayor Ed Koch.
After leaving public service Scoppetta joined the faculty of New York University School of Law as Director of the Institute of Judicial Administration. As Professor of Law he taught a seminar, "The Administration of Criminal Justice," between 1979 and 1982.
In 1980 Scoppetta cofounded with Eric A. Seiff (a colleague from the Manhattan D.A.'s Office) the law firm of Scoppetta & Seiff (now called Seiff Kretz & Abercrombie), and practiced law there privately until his return to public service in 1996.
On 11 January 1996, in the wake of the murder of Elisa Izquierdo (1989-1995) by her mother and allegations that caseworkers at New York's Child Welfare Administration missed multiple opportunities to save her, Mayor Rudy Giuliani created the Administration for Children's Services (ACS) and appointed Scoppetta its first commissioner. Scoppetta held that position until 31 December 2001.
On 1 January 2002 Mayor Michael Bloomberg appointed Scoppetta as 31st Commissioner of the New York City Fire Department. As the first commissioner after 9/11, much of Scoppetta's time was spent attending memorial services for the 343 firefighters who died in the attacks, and developing methods to address—and avoid—future tragedies. He was succeeded by Salvatore Cassano on 1 January 2010.
Throughout his long and varied career child welfare remained at the heart of Scoppetta's activities. He served on the board of the Children's Aid Society for sixteen years (and as its president between 1987 and 1993). In 1996 he founded New Yorkers for Children, the non-profit partner to the ACS. To honor his dedication, the ACS Children's Center at 492 First Avenue, Manhattan, was renamed the Nicholas Scoppetta Children's Center in 2013.
In 1963 Scoppetta married Susan Kessell, a social worker, with whom he had two children, Andrea and Eric. He died on 24 March 2016 at age 83, in hospice at Bellevue Hospital, Manhattan, next to the Nicholas Scoppetta Children's Center.
[This biography is drawn from the obituaries for Nicholas Scoppetta in the New York Times (26 March 2016) and New York Daily News (25 March 2016) and from his Wikipedia entry.]
Child welfare -- New York (State) -- New York.; Fire departments -- Officials and employees; Police corruption -- New York (State) -- New York.; Beame, Abraham D. (Abraham David), 1906-2001; Bloomberg, Michael; Giuliani, Rudolph W.; Leuci, Robert, 1940-2015; Lindsay, John V. (John Vliet); Children's Aid Society (New York, N.Y.); New York (N.Y.). Administration for Children's Services; New York (N.Y.). Fire Department; New York (N.Y.). Fire Department. Vulcan Society; New York (N.Y.). Knapp Commission
- Series I. Criminal Justice, 1974-2015 (bulk, 1978-1982); 2 Linear feet
  Scope and Contents
  This series includes material from Scoppetta's positions as Commissioner of Investigation for the City of New York (1972–1977) and Deputy Mayor for Criminal Justice (1976–1978). There is significant coverage of NYPD Detective Robert Leuci's cooperation with the Knapp Commission's investigation of police corruption. The series also contains course readings for the seminar Scoppetta taught for New York University School of Law—"The Administration of Criminal Justice"—between 1979 and 1982. A small amount of printed matter, much of it on police corruption, rounds out the series.
  Arrangement
  Series I is divided into three subseries, each arranged chronologically:
  Subseries I.A. Criminal Justice: General, 1974-2015.
  Subseries I.B. Criminal Justice: Teaching Material, 1978-1982.
  Subseries I.C. Criminal Justice: Printed Material, 1941-2000.
  - Subseries I.A. Criminal Justice: General, 1974-2015
    This subseries spans Scoppetta's years in the administrations of Mayors Beame and Lindsay in his capacity as Commissioner of Investigation for the City of New York (1972–1977) and Deputy Mayor for Criminal Justice (1976–1978). It includes a significant amount of material on NYPD Detective Robert "Bob" Leuci's cooperation with the Knapp Commission's investigations into police and criminal justice system corruption (Box 1, Folders 11-16). Leuci's involvement inspired former NYPD Commissioner Robert Daley to write Prince of the City: The True Story of a Cop Who Knew Too Much (1978), which was later filmed by director Sidney Lumet.
    The material is arranged chronologically (Box 1, Folders 1-10), followed by the contents of an accordion file Scoppetta labeled "Deputy Mayor for Criminal Justice / Det[ective]. Bob Leuci" (Box 1, Folders 11-16). Newsclippings come at the end of this subseries (Box 1, Folder 17).
    - [Criminal Justice: Beame appointments], 1974, 1976, 2011 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
      Scope and Contents Note
      Certificates signed by Mayor Abraham D. Beame appointing Scoppetta Commissioner of Investigation (1 January 1974) and Chairman of the Criminal Justice Coordinating Council (1 March 1976). Includes a printout of a 2011 e-mail from Scoppetta, "My take on my five years as DOI Commissioner."
    - [Criminal Justice: General], 1977-1981 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
    - [Criminal Justice: "Getting Away With Murder"], 1978 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
      Two copies of the Saturday Review, 10 June 1978, containing Nicholas Scoppetta's article "Getting Away With Murder: Our Disastrous Court System."
    - [Criminal Justice:] Police & Official / Corruption—Denver / Seminar, 1989 March 8 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4)
    - [Criminal Justice:] FBI Conference, 1990 June 10 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5)
      Notes from the FBI's "Advanced Public Corruption Conference" held at Phoenix, Arizona.
    - [Criminal Justice: LaGuardia oral history], 1995 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)
      Two typescript copies (one annotated) of Scoppetta's oral history interview for the LaGuardia and Wagner Archives, LaGuardia Community College, City University of New York. Includes two letters from Richard K. Lieberman, Director of the Archives.
    - [Criminal Justice:] Police Comm. Re: Litigation Mayor v City Council, 1995 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 7)
    - [Criminal Justice:] Re: Ex. Order City Council, 1995 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 8)
    - [Criminal Justice: General], n.d. (Offsite-box 1, Folder 9)
      Manuscript notes headed "What Do We Expect Our C. J. System To Do."
    - [Criminal Justice: Lindsay remembrance], 2015 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 10)
      Contains the book John V. Lindsay: 50th Anniversary Commemoration of His Election as Mayor of New York City, November 2, 1965. Reflections from More Than 260 Friends and Colleagues (McLean, Va.: International Publishers, 2015), to which Scoppetta contributed a remembrance (pp. 375-376). Lindsay appointed Scoppetta Commissioner of Investigation for the City of New York on 1 December 1972.
    - [Criminal Justice: Leuci] Relevant Notes / Leuci, 1970-1978 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 11)
      From an accordion file Scoppetta labeled "Deputy Mayor for Criminal Justice / Det[ective]. Bob Leuci."
    - [Criminal Justice: Leuci] Bob Daley, Manuscript of "Prince of the City", circa 1977 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 12)
      Partial draft of Robert Daley's book Prince of the City: The True Story of a Cop Who Knew Too Much (Boston: Houghton Mifflin, 1978). From an accordion file Scoppetta labeled "Deputy Mayor for Criminal Justice / Det[ective]. Bob Leuci."
    - [Criminal Justice: Leuci] Draft of LW's [Loudon Wainwright] Article on "Prince..." Investigation, n.d., 1981 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 13)
      With a photocopy of "A Dangerous Gift of Recall," another piece Wainwright wrote for LIFE Magazine (October 1981). From an accordion file Scoppetta labeled "Deputy Mayor for Criminal Justice / Det[ective]. Bob Leuci."
    - [Criminal Justice: Leuci], 1974, 1978 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 14)
      Includes Department of Investigation memorandum to all NYC Administrators and Agency Heads regarding the "implementation of Mayoral Executive Order No. 21 dated 19 August 1970 and Mayoral Executive Order No. 1 dated 1 January 1974." With Scoppetta's remarks to Domestic and International Scientific Planning, Annalysis and Cooperation (DISPAC) Sub-Committee Hearings, 10 January 1978, and a copy of the First Annual Report of the Office of the Deputy Mayor for Criminal Justice for the City of New York, January 1978. From an accordion file Scoppetta labeled "Deputy Mayor for Criminal Justice / Det[ective]. Bob Leuci."
    - [Criminal Justice: Leuci] Knapp Commission / "Prince of the City" Articles (2 folders), 1974-1981 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 15-16)
    - [Criminal Justice: Newsclippings], 1974, 1979, 1982, 2007 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 17)
      Five newsclippings, including Scoppetta's op-ed piece "Should Judges Jail Suspects?" from Newsday, 4 May 1979.
  - Subseries I.B. Criminal Justice: Teaching Material, 1978-1982
    In 1978 Scoppetta joined the faculty of New York University School of Law as Director of the Institute of Judicial Administration and Professor of Law. In 1979 he took over from Adjunct Professor Richard H. Kuh the seminar "The Administration of Criminal Justice," which he taught until 1982.
    Professor Kuh's course materials from the spring term of 1978 are found in Box 1, Folders 18-19. Scoppetta's adaptions follow and are arranged by seminar session number. Sessions 4, 9, and 11 were conducted on field trips, hence the lack of material for those meetings. Note the alternate version of session 12 (Box 2, Folder 4), presumably from the first (1979) iteration of the course.
    - [Kuh seminar: sessions I-XIII] (2 folders), 1978 Spring (Offsite-box 1, Folder 18-19)
    - [Scoppetta seminar: session 1] Syllabus and assignment instructions, 1979-1982 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 20)
      Includes two student papers.
    - [Scoppetta seminar: session 2] The Police, 1979-1982 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 21)
    - [Scoppetta seminar: session 3] The Prosecutor and Prosecutorial Discretion, 1979-1982 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 22)
    - [Scoppetta seminar: session 5] The Grand Jury, 1979-1982 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 23)
    - [Scoppetta seminar: session 6] Bail and Pre-Trial Detention, 1979-1982 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 24)
    - [Scoppetta seminar: session 7] Plea Bargaining (2 folders), 1979-1982 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 25-26)
    - [Scoppetta seminar: session 8] The Exclusionary Rule, 1979-1982 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 27)
    - [Scoppetta seminar: sessions 10 and 12] Sentences and The Media and Criminal Trials, 1979-1982 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 28)
    - [Scoppetta seminar: session 13] Juveniles and the Criminal Justice System (2 folders), 1979-1982 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 1-2)
    - [Scoppetta seminar: session 14] Alternatives to the Criminal Courts, 1979-1982 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 3)
    - [Scoppetta seminar, 1979 iteration: session 12] The Trial Jury, 1979-1982 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 4)
    - References, Bail & Media Law, "Criminal Court" -- Rothwax, 1979-1982 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 5)
  - Subseries I.C. Criminal Justice: Printed Material, 1941-2000
    A small amount of printed matter, mostly on the theme of police corruption.
    This material is filed chronologically by date of publication.
    - Harold Seidman, Investigating Municipal Administration: A Study of the New York City Department of Investigation (New York: Columbia University Institute of Public Administration)., 1941 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 6)
      Bound photocopy.
    - Evaluation of the Office of the Special Prosecutor, State of New York, 1975 April (Offsite-box 2, Folder 7)
      Stamped "CONFIDENTIAL / LEAA EVALUATION / REPORT #70." [LEAA = Law Enforcement Assistance Administration]
    - State of New York Commission of Investigation, The Nadjari Office and the Press, 1976 November 18 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 8)
    - Richard S. Winslow and David W. Burke, Rogues, Rascals & Heroes: A History of the New York City Department of Investigation, 1873 to 1992., 1992 June (Offsite-box 2, Folder 9)
      Bound typescript version of revised book, below.
    - Richard S. Winslow and David W. Burke, Rogues, Rascals & Heroes: A History of the New York City Department of Investigation, 1873 to 1993 (New York City Department of Investigation Corruption Prevention and Management Review Bureau). (Offsite-box 2, Folder 9)
      Published version of bound typescript, above.
    - The City of New York, Commission to Investigate Allegations of Police Corruption and the Anti-Corruption Procedures of the Police Department, Commission Report, 1994 July 7 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 10)
      Inscribed on flyleaf "NICK SCOPPETTA."
    - The City of New York, Commission to Combat Police Corruption, First Report of the Commission [loose typescript]., 1996 February (Offsite-box 2, Folder 11)
    - The City of New York, Commission to Combat Police Corruption, First Report of the Commission [bound version]., 1996 March 25 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 12)
    - The City of New York, Commission to Combat Police Corruption, The New York City Police Department: The Role and Utilization of the Integrity Control Officer, 1996 December 12 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 12)
    - The City of New York, Commission to Combat Police Corruption, The New York City Police Department's Disciplinary System: How the Department Disciplines Its Members Who Make False Statements, 1996 December 12 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 12)
    - The City of New York, Commission to Combat Police Corruption, Executive Summary, 1996 December 12 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 12)
    - Journal of Law and Policy vol. IX, no. 1., 2000 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 13)
      The David G. Trager Public Policy Symposium, "Behind Closed Doors: Secret Justice in America." Scoppetta sat on Panel III: Secrecy and the Juvenile Justice System. With an offprint of Panel III papers.
- Series II. Child Welfare, 1988-2014 (bulk, 1988-2008); 5.5 Linear feet
  This series contains items dating from before, during, and after Scoppetta's tenure as first Commissioner of the Administration for Children's Services (ACS), a position he held between 1996 and 2001. Also present are materials from New Yorkers for Children, the non-profit partner of ACS Scoppetta founded, along with some from the Children's Aid Society, where he was board president between 1987 and 1993.
  Series II is divided into three subseries, each arranged chronologically:
  Subseries II.A. Child Welfare: General, 1988-2014.
  Subseries II.B. Child Welfare: Printed Material, 1982-2012.
  Subseries II.C. Child Welfare: Audiovisual, 1996-2002.
  - Subseries II.A. Child Welfare: General, 1988-2014
    Early in his career Scoppetta worked for the Society for the Prevention of Cruelty to Children (the same agency that placed him in foster care at the age of five), but this subseries does not extend that far back. Instead it picks up a few years before his 1996 appointment as first commissioner of the newly-created Administration for Children's Services (ACS), carries through until his departure at on 31 December 2001, and continues until shortly before his death.
    The material is arranged chronologically, with general items preceding the contents of specialized accordion files Scoppetta labeled "Child Welfare & ACS" (Box 5, Folders 7-12); "Reference Child Welfare" (Box 5, Folders 13-15); "Child Welfare / Important Reference" (Box 6, Folders 1-3); and "Child Fatality" (Box 6, Folders 4-8). The final folder in this subseries (Box 6, Folder 12) contains restricted material on the Elisa Izquierdo murder case (see the container list for details).
    - [Child Welfare: General], 1989-1990 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 1)
    - [Child Welfare: General], 1991 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 2)
    - [Child Welfare: General], 1993-1994 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 3)
    - [Child Welfare: General] (2 folders), 1995 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 4-5)
    - [Child Welfare: General] (3 folders), 1996 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 6-8)
      Folder 6 includes letters from Manhattan Borough President Ruth Messinger, Chief Judge of the State of New York Judith Kaye, Queens County District Attorney Richard A. Brown, and Congress Member for New York's 14th District Carolyn B. Maloney, congratulating Scoppetta on his appointment as first commissioner of the Administration for Children's Services.
    - [Child Welfare: General] (3 folders), 1997 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 9-11)
    - [Child Welfare: General] (2 folders), 1998 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 12-13)
    - [Child Welfare: General] (2 folders), 1999 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 14-15)
    - [Child Welfare: General] (2 folders), 2000 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 16-17)
      Folder 16 includes a program from the ribbon cutting ceremony (16 November 2000) for the ACS Children's Center at 492 First Avenue, Manhattan, and architectural specifications for the building, which was renamed the Nicholas Scoppetta Children's Center in 2013.